A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, Ankara, Turkey, RG 6, SG 19 FA399
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, field offices, Ankara, Turkey, RG 6, SG 19
1968-1978
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation. Ankara (Turkey)
Rockefeller Foundation
FA399
6.62 Cubic Feet 6 legal document boxes, 10 letter document boxes.
16 document cases 202 files
Other Finding Aids note
Other available finding aids describing Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices include:
FA395 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, Paris.
FA396 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, New Delhi, India.
FA397 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, Cali, Colombia.
FA398 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, Mexico.
File Plan note
RG 6.19.
Organization of the Foundation's archives:
RG 1 Projects
RG 2 General Correspondence
RG 3 Administration, Program and Policy
RG 4 China Medical Board
RG 5 International Health Board/Division
RG 6 Field Offices
RG 7 Treasurer's Office
RG 8 Comptroller
RG 9 Personnel
RG 10 Fellowships
RG 11 Information Services
RG 12 Diaries
RG 13 Oral Histories
RG 14 Counsel
RG 15 Secretary
RG 16 Minutes and Officers Actions
RG 17 Dockets
RG 18 Declinations (100F)
RG 19 Non-textual Materials
RG 20 Communications Office.
Scope and Contents note
The Mideast Wheat Research and Training Project records contain general correspondence and administrative documents pertaining to the Turkish wheat stations and the various foundations and institutions connected to wheat research in Turkey during the 1970s. Correspondence, reports, and printed material detail the Center's wheat research work and plant breeding and its interactions with Turkish authorities and with other agricultural institutes and university agronomists. This collection documents the day-to-day work of the Center; for materials regarding the establishment and administration of the Wheat Research Center one should consult the files on Turkish Wheat Research in the Rockefeller Foundation project files, RG 1, Accession 83, Series 105 (804).
Biographical/Historical note
The Mideast Wheat Research and Training program was a project funded by the Rockefeller Foundation to help with crop research and agricultural production in Turkey. The program included breeding of adapted varieties of both spring and winter wheat for various ecological conditions, training for wheat scientists from cooperating countries, and advice and assistance in the development of the local research and production programs. In September 1967 the Rockefeller and Turkey began negotiations for the Rockefeller Foundation to participate in the development of the national wheat program. By July 1, 1970, the Turkish Wheat Research and Training Center had been established. The Rockefeller Foundation agreed to a start-up grant of $100,000, which was to expire at the end of 1968. Rockefeller Foundation funding was extended and renewed through the 1970s. In 1977 the Rockefeller Foundation signed a final three-year extension.
Quality was not considered important at the start of the project. Rather, the point was to produce a large amount of wheat. The project pioneered an approach to the problem of a specific crop.
There were several issues with the Wheat Research Project that quickly became apparent. Initially, only fluent English speakers were eligible for overseas training. As the program developed, staff received English language instruction before going for training, but once abroad they required additional training in order to function effectively and produce. Relations with the Turkish government were also complicated, and issues arose with organization and method. There were also struggles with various governmental departments. These issues were not helped by Turkey's bureaucracy and climate of administrative instability, attributable to constantly changing governments.
Over thirteen years Turkish wheat production increased from around 10 million metric tons to 17 million with general agreement that this increase was largely owing to the wheat improvement project.
Various names were used to refer to the Wheat Research and Training Program, including: Middle East Wheat Improvement Project, Wheat Improvement Project, Wheat Research Program, Mid-East Wheat Research and Training Center, and Ankara Field Office.
Significant staff members include: Ahmet Demirlicakmak, Charles K. Mann, E. E. Saari, Jon Michael Prescott, and Bill C. Wright.
Conditions Governing Access note
Records more than 20 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Related Archival Materials note
Administrative and other files relating to the Ankara Field Office, Mid-East Wheat Research and Training Center, are found in the Rockefeller Foundation project files, RG 1, Accession 83, Series 105 (804), under Turkish Wheat Research.
Arrangement
Files are arranged in two series:
1. Wheat Research Center
2. General Files.
Green Revolution; India; Latin America; Philanthropy; Life sciences; Medical education; Medical research; Social sciences -- India; Public health; Medical sciences; Agricultural innovations; Medical research -- India; Agriculture; Agricultural innovations -- Mexico; Philanthropy -- United States; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Agriculture -- India; Colombia; Charities
- Wheat Research Center, 1
  Series arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically, following the report file on Wheat Research in Turkey.
  - Wheat Research in Turkey, 1968 August (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    "The Cooperative Wheat Research Program in Turkey: A Report to the Ministry of Agriculture and to the Rockefeller Foundation." Report prepared by Ralph W. Cummings, H.A. Rodenhiser, J.W. Gibler.
  - Budget, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    File Plan note
    40.13
  - Demirlicakmak, Ahmet, 1971-1973, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    15.1
    Biographical/Historical note
    Demirlicakmak was Director of the Wheat Research and Training Center.
  - Memoranda (to file), 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    15.7
  - Ministry of Agriculture
    15.2
    - 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newsletter, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    40.25
  - Plant Breeding, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    40.7
    File includes reports by Arthur Klatt and Bill C. Wright on work underway in Turkey.
  - Staff: Finfrock, Dwight C., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Finfrock was an Experiment Station Development Officer.
  - Staff: Lindstrom, Michael J., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Lindstrom was a Research Associate.
  - Staff: Mann, Charles K., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    In 1974, Mann was an Economist with the Rockefeller Foundation's Social Sciences Field Staff, assigned to the Middle East Wheat Project. From 1971-1974, he had been with the U.S. Agency for International Development in Ankara.
  - Wheat Stations in Turkey, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Wheat Stations: Adana, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    10.1
  - Wheat Stations: Adapazari, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    10.2
  - Wheat Stations: Ankara, 1971-1972, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    10.3
  - Wheat Station: Antalya, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    10.4
  - Wheat Stations: Diyarbankir, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    10.7
  - Wheat Stations: Edirne, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    10.5
  - Wheat Stations: Erzurum, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    10
  - Wheat Stations: Eskisehir, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    10.6
  - Wheat Stations: Izmir, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    10.8
  - Wheat Stations: Izmir, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Wheat Stations: Izmir, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Wheat Stations: Samsun, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    10.9
  - Wheat Stations: Tarus, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    10.10
  - Wheat Stations: Yesilkoy, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    10.11
- General files, 2
  This series is arranged alphabetically, with general correspondence files placed at the start.
  - Correspondence (General )
    - 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - 1972 (incoming) (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - 1972 (outgoing) (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - 1973-1974 May (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - 1974 June-December (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - 1975 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - 1976 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Aktan, Resat, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Materials relate to a Rockefeller Foundation grant to the Development Foundation of Turkey (GA SS 7615), for "Description and Analysis of Wheat Farming in Turkey with Implications for Agricultural Policy." Resat Aktan was the principal investigator for the project.
    60.61
  - Algeria, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    30.16
  - Algeria, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Egypt, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    30.12
  - Egypt, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - England, 1972-1978 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    30.17
  - Europe (General), 1975-1978 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    30
  - Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO), 1971-1976 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    30.15
  - Forced Pace Campaigns, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    Preliminary draft chapter on "Recent Forced-Pace Campaigns." Includes review of wheat program in Turkey.
  - Ford Foundation: General, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Ford Foundation: General, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    Most of the correspondence concerns the Arid Lands Agricultural Development Program.
  - Ford Foundation: India
    30.4
    - 1970 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - 1971 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Ford Foundation: Lebanon
    30.3
    Materials consist mainly of correspondence and reports relating to the Ford Foundation's Arid Lands Agricultural Development Program.
    - 1970-1971 May (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - 1971 June-December (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - 1972 January-September (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - 1972 October-December (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - 1973 January-June (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - 1973 July-December (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - 1973, One item. (Box 5, Folder 57)
      "Present Livestock Situation in the Near East and the Possibility of Developing Integrated Crop-Livestock Farming Systems." Arid Lands Agricultural Development Program, Ford Foundation, Beirut, Lebanon, 1973 March.
    - 1973, One item. (Box 5, Folder 58)
      "Progress Report of the Near East Cooperative Sorghum and Millets Crop Improvement Program." Arid Lands Agricultural Development Program, Ford Foundation, Beirut, Lebanon, 1973 April (Progress Report 1972).
    - 1974 January-April (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - 1974 May-July (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - 1974 August-December (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - 1974, One item. (Box 5, Folder 62)
      "Summary Report on the Regional Sheep and Forage Production Workshop,February 11-14, 1974, Lebanon." Arid Lands Agricultural Development Program, Ford Foundation, Beirut, Lebanon, 1974 October.
    - 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 63)
      The correspondence for 1975 is primarily outgoing.
  - Ford Foundation: Tunisia
    30.2
    - 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 64)
      Includes copy of "Accelerated Cereals Production Project Seeding Report," 1970-1971, Tunisia, Ministry of Agriculture.
    - 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - 1973 (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - 1973-1974, One item, 80 pages. (Box 5, Folder 67)
      Progress Report: Tunisia, 1973-1974. Prepared by CIMMYT in cooperation with the Technical Division of the Office of Cereals.
    - 1974 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Fulbright Commission
    30.18
    - 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - 1976 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Gallun, Robert L., 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 73)
    Gallun worked with the United States Department of Agriculture's Agricultural Research Service at Purdue University. He was an Investigations Leader in the Entomology Research Division.
  - Hungary, 1971-1975 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    30.14
  - India
    30.5 - 30.6
    The India files contain correspondence with officers in the Rockefeller Foundation field office in New Delhi and more general correspondence with Indian researchers and academics.
    - 1970 January-September (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - 1970 September-December (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - 1971 January-February (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - 1971 March-May (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - 1971 June-December (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - 1971 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - 1971 (Box 6, Folder 80A)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      Restricted - Confidential material.
    - 1972 (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - 1973 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - 1974-1977 (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - International Agricultural Development Service (IADS)
    30.1
    - 1969-1976 (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - 1973 (Box 7, Folder 84A)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 85)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 85A)
  - International Center for Agricultural Research in the Dry Areas (ICARDA)
    20.9, 30.1
    - 1976 (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - 1977 January-July (Box 7, Folder 87)
    - 1977 August-September (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - 1977 October-December (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - 1978 January-June (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - 1978 July-September (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - 1978 October-December (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - International Crops Research Institute for the Semi-Arid Tropics (ICRISAT)
    30.1, 30.7, 30.19
    - 1975 (Box 9, Folder 94)
      - 1974 (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center (CIMMYT)
    Arrangement note
    Files are often separated into incoming and outgoing correspondence.
    - 1970 (Box 8, Folder 96)
    - 1971 January-April (Box 8, Folder 97)
    - 1971 May-June (Box 8, Folder 98)
    - 1971 July-August (Box 8, Folder 99)
    - 1971 September-December (Box 8, Folder 100)
    - 1972 January-February (Box 8, Folder 101)
    - 1972 March-May (Box 8, Folder 102)
    - 1972 June-September (Box 8, Folder 103)
    - 1972 October (Box 8, Folder 104)
    - 1972 November-December (Box 8, Folder 105)
    - 1972 (Box 8, Folder 106)
      "What is CIMMYT?" paper consisting of fourteen charts designed to introduce the organization to visitors.
    - 1972 (Prescott, Jon M.) (Box 8, Folder 107)
    - 1972 (Prescott, Jon M.) (Box 8, Folder 107A)
    - 1973 January-March (Box 9, Folder 108)
    - 1973 April-May (Box 9, Folder 109)
    - 1973 June-July (Box 9, Folder 110)
    - 1973 August-October (Box 9, Folder 111)
    - 1973 November (Box 9, Folder 112)
    - 1973 December (Box 9, Folder 113)
    - 1973 (Prescott, Jon M.) (Box 9, Folder 114)
    - 1973 (Prescott, Jon M.) (Box 9, Folder 114A)
    - 1974 January-March (Box 9, Folder 115)
    - 1974 April-July (Box 9, Folder 116)
    - 1974 August-December (Box 9, Folder 117)
    - 1975 January-June (Box 9, Folder 118)
    - 1975 July-December (Box 9, Folder 119)
    - 1976 January-May (Box 10, Folder 120)
    - 1976 June-December (Box 10, Folder 121)
    - 1977 January-March (Box 10, Folder 122)
    - 1977 April-December (Box 10, Folder 123)
    - 1978 January-June (Box 10, Folder 124)
    - 1978 July-September (Box 10, Folder 125)
    - 1978 October-December (Box 10, Folder 126)
  - International Potato Center (CIP), 1973-1976 (Box 10, Folder 127)
    30.1, 30.5
  - International Potato Center (CIP), 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 128)
  - International Rice Research Institute (IRRI), 1972 (Box 10, Folder 129)
  - Iran, 1970-1972 (Box 11, Folder 130)
    30.11
  - Iran, 1973-1975 (Box 11, Folder 131)
  - Iraq, 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 132)
  - Israel, 1972-1975 (Box 11, Folder 133)
  - Kenya, 1972-1977 (Box 11, Folder 134)
  - Lebanon, 1970-1975 (Box 11, Folder 135)
  - Libya, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 136)
  - Loegering, William Q., 1971 (Box 11, Folder 137)
    Loegering was Professor of Plant Pathology at the University of Missouri.
  - Meetings, 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 138)
    40.14
  - Netherlands, 1971-1977 (Box 11, Folder 139)
    30.10
  - Pakistan, 1971-1975 (Box 11, Folder 140)
    30.13
  - Rodenhiser, H.A., 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 141)
    20.8
  - Rupert, Joseph A., 1970-1972 (Box 11, Folder 142)
    20.5
    Rupert was a research associate with the Agronomy Department of the University of California, Davis, and with the International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center. He had previously served as an associate director with the Rockefeller Foundation's agriculture program in Chile.
  - Saari, Eugene E., 1971-1972
    Saari was a Plant Pathology expert with the Ford Foundation in India and then in Lebanon (from mid-1973).
    - 1971-1973 (Box 11, Folder 143)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 11, Folder 144)
  - Saudi Arabia, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 145)
  - Stubbs, R. W., 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 146)
    Ron Stubbs was affiliated with the Institute of Phytopathological Research in the Netherlands.
  - Stubbs, R. W., 1973-1976 (Box 11, Folder 147)
  - Turkey: General
    15
    Incoming and outgoing correspondence may be separated within the files.
    - 1970-1971 (Box 12, Folder 148)
    - 1972 (Box 12, Folder 149)
    - 1973 (Box 12, Folder 150)
    - 1974 (Box 12, Folder 151)
    - 1975 (Box 12, Folder 152)
    - 1976 January-May (Box 12, Folder 153)
    - 1976 June-December (Box 12, Folder 154)
    - 1977 (Box 12, Folder 155)
    - 1978 January-May (Box 12, Folder 156)
    - 1978 June-December (Box 12, Folder 157)
  - Turkey: Istanbul, 1972-1974 (Box 12, Folder 158)
  - United Nations Development Program (UNDP), 1973 (Box 12, Folder 159)
    40.37
    General note
    One item.
    "Country and Inter-Country Programming: Turkey." UNDP assistance requested by the Government of Turkey for the period 1973-1977. Official Draft, January 1973.
  - United Nations Development Program (UNDP), 1973-1975 (Box 13, Folder 160)
  - United States: General
    20
    - 1970-1971 (Box 13, Folder 161)
    - 1972 (Box 13, Folder 162)
    - 1973 January-May (Box 13, Folder 163)
    - 1973 June-December (Box 13, Folder 164)
    - 1974 January-May (Box 13, Folder 165)
    - 1974 June-December (Box 13, Folder 166)
    - 1975 (Box 13, Folder 167)
    - 1976 January-June (Box 13, Folder 168)
    - 1976 July-December (Box 14, Folder 169)
    - 1977 (Box 14, Folder 170)
    - 1978 (Box 14, Folder 171)
  - United States: Universities (General)
    - 1976 (Box 14, Folder 172)
    - 1977 (Box 14, Folder 173)
    - 1978 January-August (Box 14, Folder 174)
    - 1978 September-December (Box 14, Folder 175)
  - United States: Kansas State University, 1970-1972 (Box 14, Folder 176)
  - United States: Michigan State University, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 177)
  - United States: Oklahoma State University, 1977-1978 (Box 14, Folder 178)
  - United States: Oregon State University
    20.6-20.7
    Incoming and outgoing correspondence is generally separated within the files.
    - 1970 (Box 14, Folder 179)
    - 1971 (Box 14, Folder 180)
    - 1972 (Box 14, Folder 181)
    - 1973 January-June (Box 15, Folder 182)
    - 1973 July-October (Box 15, Folder 183)
    - 1973 November-December (Box 15, Folder 184)
    - 1974 January-May (Box 15, Folder 185)
    - 1974 June-December (Box 15, Folder 186)
    - 1975 (Box 15, Folder 187)
    - 1976 January-May (Box 15, Folder 188)
    - 1976 June-December (Box 15, Folder 189)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 15, Folder 190)
  - United States: Washington State University, 1971-1972 (Box 15, Folder 191)
  - United States Agency for International Development: General
    15.4
    - 1970-1972 (Box 15, Folder 192)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 15, Folder 193)
      Only one item from 1973.
    - 1975 (Box 16, Folder 194)
  - United States Agency for International Development: Afghanistan, 1970-1974 (Box 16, Folder 195)
    30.8
  - United States Agency for International Development: Afghanistan, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 196)
    Report of Survey and Recommendations on Agricultural Research in Afghanistan, by Agricultural Research Review Team, 1972 October 25.
  - United States Agency for International Development: Morocco, 1970, 1972-1973 (Box 16, Folder 197)
    30.7
  - United States Department of Agriculture (Beltsville, MD), 1970-1975 (Box 16, Folder 198)
  - Winkelmann, Donald
    40.34
    Winkelmann was an economist for the International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center.
    - 1972-1973 July (Box 16, Folder 199)
    - 1973 August - 1974 (Box 16, Folder 200)
  - Yemen, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 201)
  - Yugoslavia, 1971-1975 (Box 16, Folder 202)
    30.9